Guide to the Cuban Revolution Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- David C. Stone Films and Photographs, 1969-1970; Series II
  - Films
    - Brigada "Turcios Lima" (Turcios Lima Labor Brigade)
      - Alternative Title: Speech Commemorating Achievements of Brigade, 1969; Running Time: 00:33:54
        Someone introduces the act by recognizing the labor of the cane cutters and then proceeds to the presentation of the brigade's official award of distinction by the Commander Demetrio Monzeni Villa, chief of Central Command for the armed forces of Oriente.
        The main speech is given by Miguel Plasencia, Secretary of the Communist Party of Cuba for the region of Puerto Padre, who also extends a warm greeting from Guillermo García and the chief of the armed forces, Raúl Castro. He also proposes a moment of silence in honor of the recently deceased President Ho Chi Minh of Vietnam.
        Plasencia focuses his speech on the brigade and the army, stating that the army struggles side-by-side with the people in the Harvest of the Ten Million Tons. He also favorably compares Cuba's army with those in the rest of Latin America, which he qualifies as largely parasitic and repressive. He also speaks of the need for anti-imperialist solidarity against the war in Vietnam, of the commitment of the brigade to cut seven million arrobas of cane, of the fact that already in that area the Ten Million Ton Harvest of 1970 has officially started and of his desire to see the workers "sew the sack that will seal the Ten Million Tons of sugar that has to be harvested." He also challenges them to the goal of beating another brigade named "Libertadores" and proposes carrying out a competition. He also remarks on the need to cut the cane according to the standard technique required to prevent loss of sugar from cutting the cane too far up the stalk and points out the terrible deficits that other brigades have suffered as a result. He ends his speech with the slogan, "Los 10 millones van, y de que van van," ("The Ten Million Tons Go!—And that they go, they go!").
        Another intervention clarifies the fact that Miguel Plasencia is the "godfather" of the Brigada "Ferromocha" and that the real "godfather" of "Turcios Lima" brigade is Isidro Martínez, chief of Central Command for the Mobilization of the Cuban Communist Party in the region.
        Against the backdrop of a song known as the "March of the Guerrilla," the cane cutters retire to their barracks.
        Archivo sonoro grabado en el campamento de la Brigada "Turcios Lima" donde se desarrolló un acto oficial por el arribo de esta al millón de arrobas de caña cortadas y cuya tribuna fue improvisada sobre una carreta.
        Alguien hace una introducción de reconocimiento a los macheteros y después se procede al abanderamiento a la brigada por el Comandante Demetrio Monzeni Villa, del Estado Mayor del Ejército Oriental.
        El discurso central lo efectuó Miguel Plasencia, Secretario del Partido Comunista de Cuba en el Regional Puerto Padre, quien trasmitió un saludo de Guillermo García y el Jefe del Ejército y propuso hacer un minuto de silencio en honor al desaparecido Presidente Ho-Chi-Minh.
        El orador hace referencias a la brigada y al ejército, al ejército junto al pueblo en la zafra y compara el ejército de Cuba con los demás de América Latina; habla sobre la solidaridad antiimperialista y contra la guerra de Vietnam; al compromiso de la brigada de cortar hasta 7 millones de arrobas de caña; al hecho que en esa región comenzó la zafra del 70 y allí se debía coser el saco que selle los 10 millones de toneladas de azúcar; al reto que hace otra brigada nombrada "Libertadores", con la que propone efectuar una competencia; a las normas técnicas del corte, alza, etc. y a brigadas que han tenido pérdidas elevadas. Culmina el discurso con la consigna: "Los 10 millones van, y de que van van".
        Otra intervención aclarando que Miguel Plasencia es padrino de la Brigada "Ferromocha" y de la "Turcios Lima" lo es Isidro Martínez, Jefe del Estado Mayor de Movilización del PCC en la región.
        Con las notas de la marcha del guerrillero se retiran los macheteros hacia los albergues.
        - Original film, 1969 (Box 48)
        - Sound reel [restricted] (Box 48S)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 48D1)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 48D2)
        - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 48U)
      - Alternative Title: Group Interview with Seven Members of "Turcios Lima" Voluntary Labor Brigade, 1969; Running Time: 00:12:26
        Original Reel 26.
        Film in color, shot in fragmented sequences, taken in the courtyard of a campground where the voluntary labor brigade "Turcios Lima" is housed in barracks-style buildings. The film records a group interview in which seven members of the brigade provide information about their social backgrounds prior to the Revolution, the moment when their consciousness was raised in favor of struggle against the dictatorship of Batista, and their subsequent activities. The conversation focuses on the following:
        Their families' social backgrounds (most of them are of peasant extraction) and the age at which they began to work in support of their families. Some of the men are from the sugar mill Estrada Palma (re-named "Bartolomé Masó" by the state after the Revolution, in the province known after 1975 as Granma). One of the men, Félix Pacheco, is from Guantánamo.
        The moment in which some of them join the struggle against the dictator, experience a change of consciousness, or enter into the revolutionary underground in support of urban and guerrilla fighters. Some attest to the execution by firing squad or torture of friends and family members by Batista's security forces.
        Poverty in the area in which they lived and the low scholastic level they achieved as a result. They also note their work after the triumph of the Revolution to combat these social ills.
        The composition of the brigade: long-term professional cane cutters; recruits serving military duty required of all young men in Cuba after 1961; and some officials of the FAR, Revolutionary Armed Forces of Cuba.
        Their future aspirations.
        In general, they all feel as if they have achieved very little so far and have much to do in the future.
        Película en colores, fragmentada, tomada en el patio del campamento donde labora la Brigada "Turcios Lima" durante una conversación entre siete de sus miembros, donde pueden conocerse distintos aspectos de sus vidas.
        La conversación gira alrededor de varios temas como los siguientes:
        Su procedencia social (principalmente campesina) y desde qué edad comenzaron a trabajar. Algunos proceden del central Estrada Palma (posteriormente "Bartolomé Masó" en la actual provincia de Granma) y otro nombrado Félix Pacheco procede de Guantánamo.
        Momento en que algunos de ellos se incorpora a la lucha contra la dictadura de batista, toman conciencia o entran a la clandestinidad. Algunos hacen referencia a fusilados y torturas a familiares y amigos.
        La pobreza en que vivían y el nivel de escolaridad que habían alcanzado, así como su labor posterior al triunfo de la Revolución.
        La composición de la brigada por macheteros, reclutas del Servicio Militar y oficiales de las FAR.
        Sus aspiraciones futuras.
        De manera general manifiestan no haber hecho nada aun y que tienen mucho por hacer.
        - Original film, 1969 (Box 49)
        - Sound reel [restricted] (Box 49S)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 49D1)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 49D2)
        - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 49U)
      - Miscellaneous Scenes of the Brigada "Turcios Lima" in Las Tunas Province, 1969; Running Time: 00:12:26
        Film has no sound. Original Reel 27.
        Film in color made up of fragmented sequences taken in the sugar cane district in which the voluntary work brigade named "Turcios Lima" labored for the Ten Million Ton Harvest of 1969-1970. The film features the following scenes:
        Signpost that reads "La Brigada Turcios Lima se mantendrá en los cortes hasta la últimas caña de la zafra de los 10 millones," ("The Turcios Lima Brigade will remain in the fields until the last cane of the Ten Million Ton Harvest is cut.")
        Billboard along the dirt road that reads, "Las cargas de la caballería mambisa de 1868 y 1895, la Brigada Turcios Lima los reeditará en los cañaverales para liquidar el subdesarrollo," ("The Turcios Lima Brigade will duplicate the cavalry charges of the Guerrilla Soldiers of the 1868 and 1896 Wars for Independence in order to Eliminate Under-Development.")
        Interior scenes of a workers' barracks in which someone reads a pamphlet or a magazine titled Primera Conferencia de la Organización Latinoamericana de Solidaridad (OLAS).
        Locomotive and train cars loaded with cane; wheelbarrows and houses in the background.
        Children of the region, some barefoot and without shirts, in the small village near the camp
        Rain falling, instrument for measuring rainfall, a pig, a chicken, a railroad line, the landscape, cane fields, the stockpiling center, "José Martí," where one can read the phrase "Los niños nacen para ser felices," ("Children are born to be happy") that has been painted by hand on one side of the building.
        A wheelbarrow carrying cane cutters with the flag of the PCC, or Cuban Communist Party, as they approach the camp during a downpour.
        Recreational activity in the camp with a musical group.
        Dining hall during lunch or dinner.
        Barracks in which there is a battery-operated radio.
        Película en colores, fragmentada y sin sonido, tomada en la zona cañera en que labora la Brigada "Turcios Lima" donde se pueden apreciar las siguientes escenas:
        Pancarta donde se lee: "La Brigada Turcios Lima se mantendrá en los cortes hasta la últimas caña de la zafra de los 10 millones".
        Valla a un lado del terraplén: "Las cargas de la caballería mambisa de 1868 y 1895, la Brigada Turcios Lima los reeditará en los cañaverales para liquidar el subdesarrollo".
        Interior de un albergue; alguien lee un folleto o revista titulado Primera Conferencia de la Organización Latinoamericana de Solidaridad (OLAS).
        Locomotora y vagones cargados de caña, carreta y casas.
        Niños del lugar, algunos descalzos y sin camisa en el caserío cercano al campamento.
        La lluvia cayendo, un pluviómetro, casas, un cerdo, una gallina, la línea del ferrocarril, un paisaje, cañaverales, el centro de acopio "José Martí", en una de cuyas estructuras puede leerse su frase "Los niños nacen para ser felices".
        Carreta cargada de macheteros con bandera del PCC bajo la lluvia llegando al campamento.
        Actividad recreativa en el campamento con un grupo musical.
        Comedor durante horario de almuerzo o comida.
        Albergue donde alguien tiene un radio de baterías.
        - Original film, 1969 (Box 50)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 50D1)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 50D2)
        - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 50U)
    - Central "Urbano Noris" (Sugar Mill Named Urbano Noris)
      Filmed at the sugar mill named "Urbano Noris" (known before the Revolution as "San Germán") in the Urbano Noris municipality, province of Holguín (part of the province of Oriente until 1975).
      The University of Oriente is located in Santiago de Cuba (La Universidad de Oriente radica en Santiago de Cuba.).
      - Alternative Title: Student-Led Meeting with Sugar Workers, 1969; Running Time: 00:22:18
        Original Reel 28.
        Film in color, taken of a conversation between mill workers and students from the University of Oriente, who are there carrying out their practical training. Workers respond to a number of students' questions. These questions deal with the following themes:
        The payment of overtime and the workers' attitude toward the Revolution's new policy of eliminating overtime in exchange for guaranteed, year-round work and the idea of working for moral incentives and the development of society rather than individual, monetary reasons.
        The incorporation of workers into civil defense militias at the beginning of the Revolution as a result of the need to organize the people to confront foreign aggression; the creation of the militias, workers' responsibility for cleaning and maintaining workplaces and the need for workers to serve on guard duty at their work site.
        The need to eradicate absenteeism. In this context, it becomes clear that the majority of the students were graduated from technical institutions and are also demobilized former soldiers of the armed forces, or FAR.
        The Ten Million Ton Harvest and the importance that workers should give to discipline, attendance at work, etc.
        The attitude of the forty-eight young people who have completed training at the Escuela Técnica Azucarera in order to be able to operate machinery newly imported from foreign countries.
        The eradication of the habits of arriving late to work and of working slowly during the regular work day; also the problem of those who leave early and the existence of the Consejo de Justicia Laboral, or labor supervisory council charged with punishing workers for failings in their work discipline.
        At the end of the meeting, the students and workers confirm their mutual desire to work together and a student who has been leading the session says farewell on behalf of the Communist youth. The film ends with images of the sugar mill and its four smokestacks with the following words painted on them: "San Germán," (the mill's pre-revolutionary name), "Urbano Noris" and the slogan "10 Millones Van." The last scene in the film shows a political study circle of the students.
        Película en colores, tomada durante una conversación entre trabajadores del central y estudiantes de la Universidad de Oriente, que hacen sus prácticas. Los trabajadores responden a varias interrogantes de los estudiantes acerca de:
        El cobro de las horas extra y la actitud de renunciar a ello por las garantías que tienen de la revolución, de trabajo durante todo el año y no trabajar por dinero sino por el desarrollo de la sociedad.
        La incorporación de los trabajadores a la Defensa civil a raíz del triunfo de la Revolución, por la necesidad de organizar al pueblo ante las agresiones; la creación de las milicias; el cuidado de los centros de trabajo; la guardia obrera, etc.
        La asistencia al trabajo y la erradicación del ausentismo. Se conoce que la mayoría de los jóvenes son graduados de institutos tecnológicos y desmovilizados de las FAR.
        La zafra de los 10 Millones y la importancia que dan los obreros a la disciplina, asistencia, etc.
        La actitud de los 48 jóvenes que se han preparado en la Escuela Técnica Azucarera para operar los equipos de procedencia extranjera.
        La erradicación de las llegadas tarde o poco aprovechamiento de la jornada laboral, o irse antes de tiempo y que para combatirlo existe un Consejo de Justicia Laboral.
        Acuerdan estrechar y trabajar conjuntamente y un estudiante se despide en nombre de la juventud comunista.
        Se obsaervan imágenes del central con sus cuatro chimeneas, tres de ellas rotuladas: "San Germán", "Urbano Noris" y "10 Millones Van".
        Termina con escena trunca de círculo político de los estudiantes.
        - Original film, 1969 (Box 51)
        - Sound reel [restricted] (Box 51S)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 51D1)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 51D2)
        - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 51U)
      - Alternative Title: University Students in Sugar Cane-Processing Class, 1969; Running Time: 00:27:56
        Original Reel 29.
        Film in color taken in various locations and documenting the activities of students from the Univerity of Oriente. The film features the following scenes:
        Class on the chemistry of benzene.
        Students listening to a technician explain the workings of a large sugar boiling vat.
        Class on the combustion system that fuels the vats in the sugar industry.
        Students in front of a control panel regulating the operation of a boiling vat.
        A two-story wooden building in which technical instruction takes place.
        Class on military preparedness in which students organized into a platoon participate.
        Students speaking about the role of militias and the need for combat training.
        Students playing baseball on the grounds near the sugar mill.
        Película en colores, tomada en diferentes locaciones con los estudiantes de la universidad de Oriente, donde puede apreciarse:
        Clase sobre la química del benceno.
        Estudiantes con un técnico que explica el funcionamiento de la caldera.
        Clase sobre el sistema de combustión del quemador de la caldera de la industria azucarera.
        Estudiantes frente a la pizarra de control del funcionamiento de la caldera.
        Escuela de madera de dos plantas donde se imparten asignaturas técnicas.
        Clase de Preparación militar de los estudiantes, organizados en un pelotón.
        Estudiantes hablando del papel de las milicias y de la preparación combativa.
        Estudiantes efectuando un juego de béisbol en terrenos cercanos al central.
        - Original film, 1969 (Box 52)
        - Sound reel [restricted] (Box 52S)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 52D1)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 52D2)
        - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 52U)
      - Factory Work, 1969; Running Time: 00:21:36
        Original Reel 30.
        Film in color, taken of workers as they carry out their work inside a sugar mill. The workers are seen assembling parts and equipment, and engaging in repairs, iron- and cement-work. There are also images related to the scenes documented in Original Reel 29, in which students from the University of Oriente can be seen in front of the control panel of a sugar boiling vat. Various shots of the exterior and interior areas of the mill are also included. Students and workers are seen collaborating.
        Película en colores, tomada a trabajadores mientras laboran en el interior del central en tareas de montaje de piezas y equipos, reparación, construcciones de hormigón y soldadura.
        Aparecen intercaladas imágenes relacionadas con la película No. 29, en el momento en que los estudiantes de la Universidad de Oriente se encuentran frente a la pizarra de control de la caldera.
        Indistintamente se observan escenas exteriores e interiores del central; grúas izando embalajes, montaje de equipos y piezas trabajando conjuntamente obreros y estudiantes.
        - Original film, 1969 (Box 53)
        - Sound reel [restricted] (Box 53S)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 53D1)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 53D2)
        - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 53U)
      - Student Participation, 1969; Running Time: 00:26:07
        Original Reel 31.
        Film in color, taken during a group meeting of the council of leaders of the Juventud Comunista of the "Urbano Noris" sugar mill and the students of the University of Oriente in order to evaluate the work they have done so far and their outlook for the future. In the meeting, participants talk about their attitude toward work and their political duties; their need to form an "integrated" youth with the proper consciousness; the execution of sports and cultural events in order to propagandize the Communist Youth. It is stated that labor carried out in the area of cane weighing and processing has been good and that only the part of the process, in which the sugar is refined ("los turbos"), has yet to be dealt with; that the university students must be more involved in the areas of the mill over which the Juventud Comunista exercises little control, given the lack of interest among workers in continuing their studies, the number of workers who have not achieved sixth grade levels of education, and others who should begin the Secondary School for Workers and Peasants (Secundaria Obrero Campesina, or SOC).
        Additionally, participants discuss the degrees of technical training achieved among the workers and the challenge of incorporating the workers into classes despite the fact that the mill provided facilities for them to study during their regular work hours. Based on these concerns, the young Communists and students make a number of proposals. On the one hand, they will mobilize the workers for six hours of voluntary labor in agriculture on Sunday and follow this up with a party at which they will have the opportunity to carry out political propaganda. On the other hand, they will organize political study circles ("círculos politicos") to discuss the life and death of Che Guevara among workers and students involved in the building of the thermoelectric plant. Participants will be split into groups according to their shifts that will compete with one another to show which group does a better job of participating and showing their commitment to the material being discussed. According to the revolutionary idiom of the day, this process is called "emular por turnos de trabajo."
        Película en colores, tomada durante reunión conjunta de los buroes de la UJC del central y de los estudiantes de la Universidad de Oriente, para chequear el trabajo realizado y las perspectivas futuras.
        Se habla sobre la actitud ante el trabajo y las tareas políticas; de cómo formar un joven integral; la ejecución de actividades deportivas y culturales para propagandizar las actividades de la juventud. Se plantea que el trabajo en el área del vasculador y la caldera ha sido buena y quedaría el de los "turbos", sobre haber mayor vínculo de los universitarios en áreas de poco control por la UJC, pues hay dificultades con la continuidad de estudios, otros que no alcanzan el sexto grado y otros deben comenzar la Secundaria Obrero Campesina (SOC), en la capacitación en conocimientos técnicos y sobre las dificultades en la incorporación a las clases a pesar de que el central había dado facilidades para que los obreros se capaciten durante la jornada laboral.
        Se hacen propuestas: por un lado para una movilización de seis horas a la agricultura un domingo y en la noche hacer una fiesta, la cual se aprovechará para hacer propaganda y por otro lado para hacer círculos políticos sobre la caída del Che Guevara y su vida, donde participen obreros y estudiantes y en la construcción de la termoeléctrica, emular por turnos de trabajo.
        - Original film, 1969 (Box 54)
        - Sound reel [restricted] (Box 54S)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 54D1)
        - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 54D2)
        - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 54U)
      - Alternative Title: Political Education Class Among University of Oriente Students, 1969; Running Time: 00:33:20
        Original Reel 32.